Okay, so in this video then, we are going
to discuss the cost reimbursable contract.
Now the cost reimbursable
contract then, right,
C.R contract is also known
as a cost plus contract.
Right, so it could be
called cost reimbursable
or it could be called
a cost plus contract.
Now in a cost reimbursable
or cost plus contract, the
seller is just being
reimbursed for all of their costs.
So in a straight cost reimbursable,
the seller will just be reimbursed for
their costs, so they're
not actually making
any money in a straight cost reimbursable.
But there are different variations where
the seller will be making some profit,
and we're going to talk about those in
just a second.
But in a straight cost
reimbursable contract, the
seller is just being
reimbursed for all of the costs.
So you generally use a straight cost
reimbursable contract for, say,
not for, profit organizations or
not-for-profit agencies, or let's say,
just some goodwill for your customer.
So, you know, it's a great customer.
They've given you a lot of business in the
past.
They're asking you to do a small project,
so you just do it at cost for them.
Just a very simple example.
Now, one of the key things in the
cost-reimbursable contract is that it's
always considered that the buyer has all
of the risk of the contract.
So in a cost reimburseable,
generally is considered
the buyer will have
all of the risk, right?
Because the seller doesn't really have any
incentive to control cost.
They need to bring in
additional team members,
they'll just bring in
additional team members.
They don't care about
wastage of raw materials,
right, because the buyer is going to pay.
Who cares as far as the seller is
concerned?
So the seller does not really care about
the cost, they're not controlling the
cost, the buyer has all of the
risk of the contract, and therefore
the buyer has to control all
of the costs on the project.
Now, when do you use a cost-reimbursable
contract, again from a buyer's perspective
and the kind of scenarios you have to look
out for on the exam, right?
So a cost reimbursable contract then is
going to be best suited when basically you
have no idea what the outcome is going to
be.
The outcome is unknown, right?
You don't know what the scope or the
budget or the schedule is.
It's a higher risk, high uncertainty type
of project.
We don't know what the outcome is going to
be, right?
Or the scope is going to continuously
change throughout the project.
So you can't really have a fixed price
contract in that case.
Remember, in a fixed price contract,
it's a well-understood project.
Right, when the scope is
fixed, well-understood, but
in this case, we have no
idea what the outcome is.
If you don't know what the outcome is,
if the scope can continuously change,
then that's when you'd use a cost
reimbursable contract.
We have no idea what the outcome is.
Again, remember, this is from a buyer's
perspective, and this is
from PMI's perspective.
It's a kind of scenario you have to watch
out for on the exam.
Now, some variations of a cost
reimbursable contract.
The first one here, cost plus percentage
of cost.
CPPC, cost plus percentage of cost.
So in this case, then, the seller is being
reimbursed for all of their costs,
right?
So it's a cost plus seller's being
reimbursed for all of the cost.
And then plus, they're also earning a
certain percentage of that cost.
So for example, it could be cost plus 10%.
So whatever the cost
is, the seller is being
reimbursed for all of
that cost from the buyer.
And the buyer is also paying them an
additional 10% of whatever that cost is.
So in this kind of contract, the seller
actually has an incentive
to increase costs.
they have an incentive to keep costs as
high as possible because whatever the cost
is, they're going to get a certain
percentage.
So the higher the cost, the
higher the percentage, and
that percentage is obviously
the money that they're making.
On this kind of contract, the buyer really
has to control the cost.
Then you have another variation called the
cost plus fixed fee,
CPFF, cost plus fixed fee.
So the seller is being reimbursed for all
of the costs, And then they're also going
to receive a fixed fee on top of that
cost.
And so it doesn't matter what the cost is.
They're just getting this one fixed fee.
So they don't have the incentive to
increase cost.
But at the same time, there's a cost
reimbursable.
They don't really have an incentive to
keep costs down either.
Now, another variation then is something
called the cost plus incentive fee, CPIF.
So in this case, again, the seller is
being reimburs.
for all of the costs and then plus they're
going to receive a certain incentive.
So incentive again could be
in the form of a bonus, right,
they're finished by a certain
date or meet a certain condition.
They're going to get
reimbursed for the cost, but
then they'll get this
additional bonus as well.
The incentive could also be in the form of
a cost share.
Costs of increase, buyer and sell have
agreed to share part of that cost,
similar to the fixed price
incentive fee, the FPIF,
similar to the FPIF contract
that we talked about earlier.
And then we have the CPAF, cost plus award
fee.
Now the cost plus award
fee is a little strange in the
sense that there is a
fixed fee portion to it, right?
So they're being
reimbursed for all the costs
and then there is a
fixed fee portion to it.
But then on top of that, there is a
subjective award that the seller may or
may not get, and it's purely at the
discretion of the buyer.
If we like the work that you've done,
if we're really impressed with,
say, the design of the work, or we're
really impressed with the way that you
perform the work, the efficiency of the
way that you did the work, if we're really
impressed with that, we'll give you an
additional bonus, an
additional subjective bonus.
But it's not guaranteed.
And it's purely and simply at the
discretion of the buyer.
You may, the seller may get it,
they may not get it.
And so the best way to think
of a CPAF, cost plus award
fee, the best way to think
of that is think of it as a tip.
It's a tip that the, you
know, it's discretion
of the buyer, the seller
may or may not get it.
So just like when you
go to a restaurant, you go
to a restaurant, you
look at this meal, right?
It's, you know, it's a fixed price there.
right so that would be the fixed fee
portion if you like right so you have to
pay for this meal but then it's entirely
up to you what tip you give right some
people give a tip some people don't some
people might give 5%, 15 10%, you know
whatever it is right so it's just based on
your discretion and that's really what the
CPAF is cost plus award
fee there's a fixed fee portion
to it right but then
there's a subjective award.
Best way to think of that is a tip.
So this is cost reimbursable then.
So these are the different variations then
of a cost reimbursable contract.
Again, make sure you know all the
different variations.